Guide to the Records of the Founding of the University MC.228
New York University Archives
New York University Collection of Printed Materials on the Founding of the University
1830-1982
1830-1860
New York University Archives
Wainwright, Jonathan Mayhew, 1792-1854
Council of the University of the City of New York
Mott, Valentine, 1785-1865
Lewis, Morgan, 1754-1844
MC.228
4 Linear Feet in 7 manuscript boxes and 2 half manuscript boxes
New York University (NYU) was founded in 1831. This collection contains documentation surrounding that event, as well as material from subsequent decades pertaining to NYU's early history.
Related Materials
RG 3.0.1 Records of the Office of the Chancellor
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions, but special care must be given to fragile original documents.
Arrangement
The collections is arranged in four series:
Documents Related to Founding
Early Documents
Published Articles
Clippings and Publications
Scope and Contents
The bulk of the collection is comprised of primary materials related to New York University's founding. These include the documents and manifestos the founders drafted to establish the University as well as some of the earliest articles written about NYU, recollections from students and material about the University Building. Materials also highlight certain episodes in the first half-century of the University, such as the 1881 effort to abolish the undergraduate department, resignation of the University's first Chancellor, James A. Matthews, and the firing of various professors. The collection also includes 20th-century material related to the early years of the university. Contained within the collection are clippings, correspondence, circulars, addresses and publications. Most of the material is either bound or has been photocopied.
Historical Note
New York University was founded as the University of the City of New-York in 1831. It retained this name until 1896. The University's founders envisioned the school as a departure from other American institutions of higher learning. It would be a nonsectarian university and educate the working classes with a practical and useful curriculum in modern language, sciences and politics. In 1830 a group of men, comprised of local merchants and businessmen, issued "Considerations upon the Expediency and the Means of Establishing a University in the City of New-York," addressed to the citizens of the city. They desired to expand educational opportunities beyond the "privileged class" by establishing a university to prepare young men for a variety of occupations, from merchant to physician.
The New York State Legislature officially incorporated the University of the City of New-York in 1831. In 1833 the University celebrated its first commencement and graduated three students. The University's first permanent home was completed in 1835. The ornate, marble, neo-Gothic building housed classrooms, apartments and office space as well as a chapel. Before its construction, classes were held further downtown near City Hall.
For additional information, see:
"Considerations Upon the Expediency and the Means of Establishing a University of the City of New-York," 1830; The Records of the Founding of the University; RG 1.00; Box 2, Folder 1; New York University Archives.
Dim, Joan Marans and Nancy Cricco, The Miracle on Washington Square: New York University, Lanham, Maryland: Lexington Books, 2001.
Jones, Theodore Francis, ed. New York University: 1832-1932, New York: The New York University Press, 1933.
Custodial History
The collection was compiled from various sources and donors within the University.
Wainwright, Jonathan Mayhew, 1792-1854; Anthon, George, George C. (George Christian), 1820-1877; Mason, Cyrus, 1798-1865; Council of the University of the City of New York; Gallatin, Albert, 1761-1849; Mathews, J.M. (James McFarlane), 1785-1870; Mott, Valentine, 1785-1865; Lewis, Morgan, 1754-1844; Loomis, Elias, 1811-1889; Frelinghuysen, Theodore, 1787-1862; Henry, C.S. (Caleb Sprague), 1804-1884; Draper, John William, 1811-1882; New York University. Administration; New York University -- History
- Series I: Documents Related to Founding, 1830-1956
  - Correspondence re: Journal of the Proceedings of the Literary Convention, 1956 September 23 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - 1830 Establishment Papers (reproductions), undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Journal of the Proceedings of a Convention of Literary and Scientific Gentlemen (multiple copies), 1830 October, 1933 March (Box 1, Folder 3-6, Box 8, Folder 1, Box 9)
  - "Considerations Upon the Expediency and the Means of Establishing a University in the City of New York" by Jonathan Mayhew Wainwright, 1830 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Memorial to the New York State Legislature from the Council of the University of the CIty of New York (typewritten copy), 1830 December (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - An Address to the Citizens of New York on the Claim of Columbia College and the New University to Their Patronage, 1830 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Series II: Early Documents, 1833-1929
  - An Exposition of the Reasons for the Resignation of Some of the Professors in the University of the City of New York by Henry Vethake, John Mulligan and John Torrey (4 copies), 1833 November (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - A Letter to the Councillors of the University of the City of New York: From the Professors of the Faculty of Science and Letters, 1838 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - An Exposition by the Council of the University of the City of New York, Respecting the Late Measures of Retrenchment Adopted in That Institution, and Which Led to the Dismissal of Some of the Professors in the Faculty of Science and Letters (3 copies), 1838 (Box 6, Folder 3, Box 8, Folder 2)
  - History of the Controversy in the University of the City of New York; With Original Documents and an Appendix (2 copies), 1838 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - The University of New York and the Professors Notes of Investigation by William C. Noyes, 1839 April-May (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Report of the Regents of the University in Relation to the University of the City of New York (2 copies), 1840 January (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Circular of a Committee of the Council of the University of the City of New York, 1847 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Circular of a Committee of the Council of the University of the City of New York (2 copies), 1848 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Report of the Committee on Literature on the Petition of Hamilton and Geneva Colleges, and New York University, 1859 February (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - "Narrative and Documents Connected with the Displacement of the Professor of the Greek Language and Literature in the University of the City of New York," by George C. Anthon, A.M. (4 copies), 1851 April 2 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Circular of the Faculty, 1850 September (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Events of 1881 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Faculty Circular and Newspaper Clippings, 1881 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Literary Digest Controversy Adjusted, 1929 November 15 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - An Act Incorporating the University of the City of New York, passed April, 18, 1831 (Box 8, Folder 3)
- Series III: Published Articles about NYU, 1853-1883
  - "Temple Court" by Cornelius Mathews [an article descriptive of New York University While Located at Clinton Hall, 1832-1835], 1883 July (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Description of the University Building from The Family Magazine, undated (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Putnam's Monthly: Educational Institutions of New York, 1853 (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Series IV: Clippings and Publications, 1829-1982
  - New York University: W.R. Martin's Historical Collections, 1829-1830 (Box 4)
  - University of the City of New York, 1836 (Box 4)
  - Fort Washington by Reginold Pelham Bolton, 1902 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Washington and His Army in Bergen County by Arthur J. O'Dea, correspondence, 1957 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Around the Square, 1830-1890, ed. Mindy Cantor (3 copies), 1982 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - "My Old Professors" by F.N. Zabriskie, 1884 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Clippings of the Inauguration of Chancellor Frelinghuysen, 1839 (Box 5, Folder 5)